Guide to the H. L. Mencken Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
H. L. Mencken collection
1905-1972
YCAL MSS 794
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.09
(26 boxes)
The H. L. Mencken Collection consists of writings, correspondence, and other material by and relating to the American author H. L. Mencken. Works documented in the collection include early poems, short works of opinion and journalism, and longer books such as The American Language (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1919) and Treastise on the Gods (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1930). Writings consist of drafts in various stages, setting manuscripts, and proofs, many of which are corrected. Several manuscripts are signed and inscribed by Mencken to journalist and collector Bradford F. Swan. Correspondence is chiefly outgoing and relates to the themes that are prominent in Mencken's writings (American politics, language, and society) as well as to the business of Mencken's writing. In addition to writings and correspondence by Mencken, the collection includes writings about Mencken, particularly the work of Margaret Lappin, sister of his longtime secretary, Rosalind Lohrfinck.
Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. Acquisitions Prior to 1973. II. 1973 Acquisition.
H. L. Mencken (1880-1956)
Henry Louis Mencken (1880-1956), American journalist and author; his books include The American Language (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1919) and Treatise on the Gods (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1930).
Related Materials
Associated material: Margaret Lappin papers relating to H.L. Mencken (YCAL MSS 376). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The H. L. Mencken Collection consists of writings, correspondence, and other material by and relating to the American author H. L. Mencken. Works documented in the collection include early poems, short works of opinion and journalism, and longer books such as The American Language (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1919) and Treastise on the Gods (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1930). Writings consist of drafts in various stages, setting manuscripts, and proofs, many of which are corrected. Several manuscripts are signed and inscribed by Mencken to journalist and collector Bradford F. Swan. Correspondence is chiefly outgoing and relates to the themes that are prominent in Mencken's writings (American politics, language, and society) as well as to the business of Mencken's writing. In addition to writings and correspondence by Mencken, the collection includes writings about Mencken, particularly the work of Margaret Lappin, sister of his longtime secretary, Rosalind Lohrfinck.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection is primarily a gift of Bradford F. Swan, 1947-1952, and bequest of Margaret R. Lappin, 1973. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
American literature -- 20th Century; Americanisms; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; English language -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953; United States -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Lappin, Margaret R.; Lohrfinck, Rosalind; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Swan, Bradford F. (Bradford Fuller)
- Acquisitions Prior to 1973, 1; 5.63; (14 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  General
  Former call number: Za Mencken.
  - A Book of Prefaces, draft, typescript, 1917; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Address of H. L. Mencken at the dinner of the American Philosophical Society," draft, typescript carbon, signed, 1948 November 4
  - "The advance of honorific science," draft, typescript, corrected, undated
  - "The American language," drafts, typescript carbon, 1945
  - "The American language: Hell and its outskirts," draft, typescript carbon, 1948
  - "American literature," draft, typescript, signed, 1931
  - "American profanity," draft, typescript carbon, 1944
  - "The American scene," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1927
  - "The Anglo-Saxon," printed version, corrected and signed, 1924, undated
  - [Answers to questions sent by Roger Butterfield of Life ], typescript carbon, annotated, 1946 June
  - [Articles written for the Baltimore Evening Sun ], drafts, typescript carbon, signed, 1948 September-November
  - "Auroral," draft, typescript, 1898?
  - [Author's note for The Days of H. L. Mencken ], drafts, typescript carbon, 1947
  - "A beautiful worm turns," draft, typescript carbon, 1934 July 4
  - "Bulletin on Hon.," draft, typescript carbon, 1946
  - "Days of change," draft, typescript carbon, 1929 July
  - "Days of innocence: Memories of obituary orgies," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, 1943
  - "Days of innocence: The spirit of service," draft, typescript carbon, 1943 July 5-9
  - "Days of innocence: Surdi audiunt," draft, typescript carbon, 1943 May 3-4
  - "Designations for colored folk," draft, typescript carbon, undated
  - "Disaster in Moronia," draft, typescript carbon, 1939 May 19
  - "The end of Prohibition," printed version, corrected, 1932 June 30
  - "Etymological notes," draft, typescript, 1947 July
  - "Finale of the Rogues' March," printed version, corrected, 1926
  - "The fireplace in the downstairs sitting room," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1945
  - "Footnote on criticism," printed version, corrected and signed, 1922
  - "The Green Mountains," draft, typescript carbon, 1931 July 10
  - "H. L. Mencken, by H. L. Mencken," draft, typescript carbon, 1923 October 12-15 (Box 2)
  - "Home to roost," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1948 July 29-30
  - "Huneker: A memory," printed version, corrected and signed, 1922
  - "The husbandman," printed version, corrected and signed, 1924
  - "Killers," draft, typescript, corrected, 1928
  - "The language of the flour-mill," draft, typescript, 1948
  - "Leaves from a diary," draft, typescript carbon, 1934 October 11
  - "Lecture at Cooper Union, New York," draft, typescript, signed, 1939
  - "The life of an artist," draft, typescript carbon, 1948 January 17-18
  - "Maryland," draft, typescript carbon, undated
  - "Metamorphosis," draft, typescript carbon, 1934 April 18-19
  - "Names for Americans," draft, typescript, corrected, 1947 July 8
  - "New Deal No. 1," printed version, corrected, 1934 December 31
  - [Note concerning the beginning of American Speech ], draft, typescript carbon, 1945 December
  - [Note on impersonal causation], draft, typescript, corrected, undated
  - [Note on journalism], draft, typescript, signed, undated
  - [Note on recent coinages of words in England, with vocabulary], draft, typescript, corrected, 1944 February
  - [Notes on American given names], draft, typescript, 1943
  - "On passing the island of San Salvador," fair copy, typescript, 1905
  - "Proposed changes in the treatise on right and wrong," notes, typescript carbon, 1948
  - "Preface" [to Dreiser's An American Tragedy ], drafts, typescript carbon, 1946 January 27
  - "Preface to the revised edition" [of Treatise on the Gods ], drafts, typescript carbon, 1946
  - [Review of] American College Dictionary, draft, typescript, corrected, undated
  - [Review of] American Names, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1948 February 10
  - [Review of] American Sayings, draft, typescript carbon, 1946 July
  - [Review of] The English Dictionary from Cawdrey to Johnson, drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1946 July 8
  - [Review of] "Meditation," by Major Owen Hatteras, D.S.O. [pseudonym], draft, typescript carbon, 1919 April
  - [Review of] Names on the Land, drafts, typescript carbon, 1945
  - [Review of] Teaching English Usage, drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1948
  - [Review of] The surnames of Scotland, drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1946
  - "The ruins of Carthage," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1934
  - "The Sahara of the Bozart," printed version, corrected, 1920, 1947
  - "Stare decisis," draft, typescript carbon, 1944 July 1-8
  - "Verbs new and old," draft, typescript carbon, 1947
  - "Why I eschew the theatre," drafts, typescript carbon, 1946-1947
  - "The worship of muscle," draft, typescript carbon, 1931 March 25
  - "Treatise on the Gods", undated
    - Setting manuscript, undated; 5 (Box 3)
    - Galley proofs, 1946; 2 (Box 4)
  - "The American language: Supplement I", undated
    - First draft, typescript, corrected, undated; 2 folders
    - Draft, typescript carbon, undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Revised draft, typescript carbon, corrected and signed, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Proofs, undated
    - Proofs, corrected, undated (Box 7)
  - "The American language: Supplement II"
    - Excerpts, drafts, typescript and carbon, undated; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Draft, typescript, signed, 1947
    - Errata, draft, typescript, corrected, 1948 May 23-June 3
    - Proofs, 1948 March 22; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - "A new dictionary of quotations"
    - Revisions for second printing, page proofs, undated (Box 10)
    - Revisions for third printing, plate proofs, 1946 May
  - Letters to Bradford F. Swan, 1928-1948 March 22; 7 folders
  - Letters to Bradford F. Swan, 1948 April 1-1956; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Letters to H. Glenn Brown, 1946
  - Letters to Henry Seidel Canby, 1933-1936
  - Letter to unidentified recipient, rejecting a submission to Smart Set, [no year] November 29
  - Letters to Mr. Duren, [1925?]
  - Letters to Roger S. Eggleston, 1945-1946
  - Letter to Mr. Emmons, 1928 September 7
  - Telegram to John R. Frazier, 1946 December 31
  - Letter to Isaac Goldberg, 1935 August 8
  - Letter to Marion Bloom, 1922 January 11
  - Letter to Mr. Leippert, 1927
  - Letter to Amy Loveman, [193-] January 23
  - Note to Michael Monahan, 1920 March 12
  - Letter to Dr. Myerson, 1933 March 11
  - Letter to Mrs. Duncan, [no year] October 26
  - Agreement between H. L. Mencken, Cinema (Canada) Pictures Limited, and John Labatt concerning film rights to A Neglected Anniversary, negative photostat of typescript, undated
  - Letters to Alfred L. S. Wood, 1924-1926
  - Letters to Mr. [Robert] Lull, 1941-1944
  - Obituary of H. L. Mencken, by Bradford F. Swan, galley proof, 1950
  - "Back of Brimstone Corner," by Bradford F. Swan, galley proofs, 1951
  - Obituary profile of H. L. Mencken, by Malcolm Johnson, draft, typescript, undated
  - Letters to George R. Hyde, 1923, 1926
  - Letter to Mr. Epstein, 1927
  - Letter to Louis Adamic, 1926 September 23
  - Letters to Pat [Knopf], 1934
  - Letter to [Alfred] Knopf, [1921] February 21
  - Letter to A. A. Knopf, [1921] February 7
  - "The rondeau of riches," fair copy, typescript, undated
  - Letters to Nesbit, undated
  - Letter to Miss Sieve, 1927 December 6
  - Letter to Mr. Spier, 1921 March 5
  - Letters to the Princess Troubetzkoy [Amélie Rives], 1921-1922
  - Manuscript inscription on the stationery of Howes Norris, Jr., 1918 April 18
  - Postcard to Mr. Thompson, [no year] July 20
  - Letters to unidentified recipient., undated
  - Letters to Dudley Nichols, 1928-1943
  - "The Library," draft, typescript, reviews, and page proofs, undated
  - Baltimore Sun articles on the Johns Hopkins hospital by H. L. Mencken, 1937
  - "Making a Mencken Collection," by Bradford F. Swan, typescript, circa 1949
  - Letters from Julian P. Boyd to Bradford F. Swan, 1948
  - Untitled undergraduate thesis on H. L. Mencken, by Wheeler Sammons, Jr., typescript, circa 1947
  - Press releases concerning H. L. Mencken and his books, from the Associated Press, Alfred A. Knopf, and Thomas Y. Crowell Company, typescript and typescript carbon, undated
  - Article on terms in the argot of the American stage, written for Theatre Arts, draft, typescript carbon, undated
  - Overture to Charles Honce's For Loving a Book, draft, typescript carbon, 1945 June 29
  - Note for Knopf catalog, concerning the revised edition of Mencken's Treatise on the Gods, typescript carbon, 1945 November 4
  - Articles for Word Study, drafts, typescript carbon, 1946 May
  - Article on Norman Thomas, draft, typescript carbon, 1948 October 17
  - Speech prepared for a public dinner on the retirement of Judge Eugene O'Dunne, draft, typescript, 1945 June 25
  - Answers to a questionnaire prepared for the Toronto Saturday Night, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 July
  - Foreword to Burges Johnson's The lost art of profanity, draft, typescript carbon, 1948 June 11
  - Rejected first title page for the 4th edition of The American language, with proof of revised version, undated
  - Letters to H. L. Mencken from Burton Bascoe and Meredieth Janvier, 1929, 1945
  - "A Mencken chrestomathy," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Address on the H. L. Mencken Collection, by Bradford F. Swan, typescript and carbon, circa 1949
  - Bradford F. Swan correspondence and papers
    - Kaiser, Clara Huston, 1945-1950
    - Brown, Lloyd A., 1949
    - Eggleston, Roger, 1946
    - Black, Robert K., 1945-1946
    - Lists of Swan's Mencken collection, 1945
    - Letters from Meredith Janvier to Bradford F. Swan, 1930-1933
    - Bradford F. Swan correspondence concerning his H. L. Mencken collection, 1945-1950
  - Coat of arms. Pencil drawing., undated
  - Interview on music, draft, typescript, corrected, undated
  - Letters to Mr. Kelley, 1939 October
  - Address to the XXV Club of Providence at Hope Club, by Bradford F. Swan, typescript, corrected, 1955
  - Letters to Ben Abramson, 1941, 1943
  - Letter to Mr. Callahan, [no year] October 19
  - Letters to Fania Marinoff, 1928-1955; 2 folders
  - [Receipt, acknowledging payment for the story "When magic met muscle"], 1901 January 5
  - Letters to Joseph Smith Fletcher, 1931-1934
  - Letter to Madeleine Boyd, [no year] March 2
  - Letter to Isaac Goldberg, 1925 December 29
  - Letter to Witter Bynner, 1923 September 18
  - Card inscribed to James Waldo Fawcett, 1921 [December 24]
  - "Henry Louis Mencken: Critic of his times," senior thesis, Princeton University, typescript carbon, 1956 April 4
  - "The American Language: Supplement I," footnote, typescript, undated
  - "The current suffixes," draft, typescript
  - "Taxicab drivers," draft, typescript carbon, undated
  - Letters to Nils F. Brown, 1925-1956
  - [List of foreign translations of the works of H. L. Mencken], typescript, undated
  - Letters to Willard Huntington Wright, 1909-1935; 6 folders
  - Letters to Bradford F. Swan, 1950-1957; 3 folders
  - Letters to Pat O'Mara, [1930]-1946
  - Bradford F. Swan Mencken Collection bookplates, undated
  - Bradford F. Swan Mencken Collection bookplates, two metal plates, undated (Box 14)
  - Liberian flag, silk, 4" by 5"
  - "Old Dr. Mencken's Hell Salts," metal canister containing an unidentified powder, undated (Box 22)
  - Siegel, John F. Crayon sketch of H. L. Mencken, circa 1923 June (Box 23)
  - Hood, Richard. Engraving plate of H. L. Mencken, with proofs, 1930 (Box 23)
  - Photograph of Bradford F. Swan and H. L. Mencken, undated (Box 23)
  - Photograph of a cow by H. L. Mencken, in an envelope addressed to Carl Van Vechten, 1941 (Box 23)
  - Rosenshine, Annette, bronze caricature of H. L. Mencken (Box 24)
  - Photographs of H. L. Mencken, 1910s-1930s; 8
- 1973 Acquisition, 2; 1.96; (6 boxes)
  Custodial History
  Material filed under this heading was willed by Rosalind Lohrfinck, Mencken's secretary, to Margaret Lappin, before it was acquired by the Yale University Library in 1973.
  Organized under five headings: Writings of H. L. Mencken, Correspondence of H. L. Mencken, Material Relating to Margaret Lappin's Writings on Mencken, Margaret Lappin and Rosalind Lohrfinck Correspondence, and Other Papers.
  Former call number: Uncat Za MS Mencken.
  - Writings of H. L. Mencken
    - Reporting from conventions, drafts, typescript, 1948 (Box 15)
    - "Podunk," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated
    - "Names for Americans," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated
    - "The New Puritanism" (Part I), draft, typescript, corrected, undated
    - "The birth of new verbs," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated
    - "Booboisie," draft, typescript, corrected
    - "The American: His language," draft, typescript carbon, 1913 August
    - "The American," draft, typescript carbon, 1913 June
    - "Secret memoirs," typescript carbon, undated; 5 folders
    - "The American language," draft, typescript, corrected, undated
    - "What the people of American towns call themselves," draft, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated
  - Correspondence of H. L. Mencken
    - Joyce, James (incoming), 1915-1926 (Box 16)
    - Lohrfinck, Rosalind (outgoing), 1930-1949, undated; 2
    - Lappin, Margaret (outgoing), including copies, 1922-1949; 8
    - "Catherine" (outgoing), 1945 December 31
    - Dr. Colston (outgoing), 1949 January 11
    - Knopf, Blanche (outgoing), 1927 April 11
    - Mr. Fitzell (outgoing), 1946 December 28
    - Providence Journal (outgoing), 1946 January 28
    - Shaw, George Bernard (outgoing), 1939 October 2
    - General correspondence (outgoing), retained carbons, 1926
    - General correspondence (incoming), 1949, undated
  - Material Collected for Margaret Lappin's Writings on Mencken
    - Speeches by H. L. Mencken, drafts, typescript carbon, undated (Box 17)
    - Various short writings by Mencken, drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, 1939-1949, undated
    - Notes on Mencken by Rosalind Lohrfinck, 1949-1952
    - Notes and documents relating to H. L. Mencken's illness, 1948-1956, undated
    - Margaret R. Lappin correspondence, 1926-1964, undated
    - Correspondence and other material relating to An Unpleasant Evening with H. L. Mencken, 1972; 2 folders
    - "If we can keep the tree," by Margaret Lappin, drafts, typescript, and related correspondence, 1951-1971
    - "It wasn't easy to be H. L. Mencken," drafts, typescript carbon, and related correspondence, 1971-1972
    - "Charlatanry of the learned," draft, typescript carbon, and related material, 1926-1930, 1970; 2 folders
    - "Rosalind", 1939, 1967, undated
    - "Material for Vol. II of my projected book on HLM and RCL", undated
    - "Request for microfilming", undated
    - "Vol II," draft, typescript, corrected, and related material, undated
    - "Merry Christmas from Mr. Mencken," draft, typescript, and related material, 1970-1971
    - "Documentation"
    - Unsorted loose notes, undated
  - Margaret Lappin and Rosalind Lohrfinck Correspondence
    - Adler, Betty, 1964-1972 (Box 18)
    - Dudek, J. B., 1958
    - As I saw Mencken, related correspondence, 1957-1971
  - Other Material
    - Yale University Library Gazette, Volume 24, Number 4, 1950 April
    - Program for "Reunion in Vienna," The Erlanger Theatre, 1931
    - Program for "Three's a Crowd," Erlanger Theater, 1931
    - Photographs of H. L. Mencken, 1927, undated
    - "The Mencken Collector," Catalogs number 1 and 2, 1972-1973
    - Clippings, 1912-1972; 11 folders (Box 19)
    - Silver plate, undated (Box 20 (Oversize))
    - Door knocker, undated
- Other Acquisitions, 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence by and relating to H. L. Mencken.
  - Letters to Joseph W. Bishop, 1945-1947 (Box 25)
  - Bradford F. Swan correspondence; letter from Mencken to Mr Gancher, [1933], 1951, 1960
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Bradford F. Swan, 1962 February.
  - Bradford F. Swan correspondence relating to Mencken, 1956-1968
    Gift of Bradford F. Swan, 1969.
  - Letters from Mencken to Dr. Clara Kaiser; letter from Dr. Kaiser to Bradford Swan, 1928, 1964
    Gift of Bradford Swan, 1965
  - Letter from Mencken to Dr. John J. Mulleedy; note from Dr. Mulleedy to the Providence Journal, 1946, 1960
    Gift of Bradford F. Swan, 1964.
  - Letters to John Toohey and Alexander Woollcott, undated
    Purchased from Walter Benjamin on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1965.
  - Letters to Pierre Bosman, [1928]-1930
    Purchased from Kenneth W. Rendell, Inc. on the Beinecke bequest, 1974.
  - Letter from Anne S. Kinsolving Brown to Bradford F. Swan, 1973
    Gift of Bradford F. Swan, 1973.
  - Letters to Carroll Frey, 1923-1924 (photocopies), undated
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Review of "Meditation" (From Acquisitions prior to 1962), 1919 (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - Clippings (From 1973 Acquisition), 1938-1971